Are we really calling it vibe coding
now? Do we have to? Because I'm not such
a fan of that term vibe coding. I just
find it silly and kind of weird and it
doesn't really speak to what to me is
like so exciting about actually coding
with AI. I' I'd rather just call it
building with AI or coding with AI. And
I'm finding that these days, you know,
I'm still obviously writing a lot of
code, but I think I might even be
prompting and communicating with my AI
assistant or agent even more than
writing actual code. I'm not vibe
coding. I'm building with AI using
cursor. All right, so let's uh let's
take a look. I'm I'm going to sort of
just like kind of walk through uh my
cursor setup here in the product that I
happen to be currently working on and
that is you know building out the
components product at
instrumental.dev. It's a components
library product for Ruby on Rails. I'm
in the thick of it. It's a really
complex product from a programming
standpoint and cursor and AI has been a
really fantastic assistant for me in in
getting this thing built. All right. So,
I'm going to start with a couple of like
quick tips. Uh things that I find
myself, you know, using uh quite often.
This isn't going to be the most in-depth
cursor manual or tutorial. You can find
that kind of stuff elsewhere. I'm just
going to walk through what I am doing in
my workflow and how I have it set up.
So, let's start with uh cursor rules.
You may have heard about this. It's a
really good feature, but it's actually
one of these things, and there's going
to be a lot of these things where it's a
really cool feature that I am not using
or at least not using enough. I'm going
to go into uh settings, go to cursor
settings, and then under rules, you'll
find this thing called user rules.
Actually, right now, I only have a
single line in here. I'm sure this is a
big opportunity for me to uh add to my
rules or I know that there are a lot of,
you know, forums and things online where
you where people share uh their cursor
rules. Those are probably worth digging
into. But I'll I'll be completely
honest. Cursor has gotten so good and
the models and the AI and the different
modes have gotten so good that I I
haven't felt the need to modify my
rules. Although I do have one in my
project, which I'll show you in a
second. But the only rule that I added
here a few weeks ago was just to tell
it, hey, never try to remove my own
comments in my code because I happen to
be the type of person who actually likes
to write a lot of code comments. Um,
especially in products like this one
that are really really complex with a
lot of uh logic, you know, that go in
all sorts of different directions. I
like to have these comments everywhere.
I find that they actually help me dive
right back into the code and maintain
and and remember what my thinking and my
strategy and and the and the systems
design was around each thing. I think
that adding these comments also helps
train the AI on understanding what each
section of code is doing. Although the
AI is probably even better at doing that
than I am, but um yeah, I just find it
it's it's like a quality of life kind of
thing where I always want these comments
to be present. But I did notice that the
AI was always removing them. Like when
it would give me a suggested piece of
code and some updates to make, it would
just wipe out these comments that I I
wanted them there for a reason. So, um
that's why I did uh how do I get back to
my cursor rules? I don't know if cursor
rules is available in this menu. You
know how like cursor came from VS Code?
It's like a fork of VS Code. They have
their own settings and their rules here.
So, not quite sure how to like navigate
to it other than getting to it from the
menu. As you can see, I don't come in
here very often, but one of the newer um
updates in cursor is now you can add a
folder in your actual project. So, up
here, if you have a folder called cursor
and then inside that um a folder called
rules, you can create these uh MDC
files. I'm actually not even sure what
MDC stands for. I probably should do
more research before I do the these
videos, but again, this is sort of just
more of like a day in the life and what
my projects look like. Now, in this
project, this particular project, which
is a Rails components project, I'm
building a gem for for Rails. It's not
an actual Rails application. This is a
gem that you would install into an
application. And so that's why I created
this about file where I'm saying this is
a Ruby on Rails gem which users will
install in their gem file uh in their
host Ruby on Rails application provides
a collection of generators that um that
can help you um install components into
your Rails project. So, I wanted to make
that really clear to the AI because
without this, it's going to treat all
this Ruby and Railsish code as if it's
its own Rails application, which is not
correct, right? Like, this is some
pretty important context for the AI to
have. And I did find that once I added
this a few weeks ago, every interaction
that I had with AI was was much more
accurate in terms of what I want to
actually build into my project. So, you
know, you can add multiple custom rules
that are specific to your current
project um in this cursor folder. Now,
let's go into some of these like newer
features that just started rolling out
in the last few months. I put my AI chat
panel on the left side and I like to
have my files on the right side and I
can, you know, um open and close it with
I mapped command L to that. You know,
cursor has been updating this little
interface uh quite a bit. So now I think
it defaults to agent mode. And I'll be
honest, I never leave agent mode. I I
never use ask and I never use manual. My
sense is that agent mode is sort of a
combination of all these things. Like
ask is really for if you just want to
like ask it questions about your
codebase, but you don't actually want to
make any changes. I guess it's sort of
good if you for situations where you
want to like plan out a feature or maybe
you're diving into a codebase that
you're new to and you need to understand
how it all works. I guess you could use
ask for that, but you could also just
ask questions when you're in agent mode,
too. So, I don't really see the point of
of switching. Manual mode, I think, is a
little bit targeted, but as I'll talk
about here in a second, like I actually
work in a very targeted way when I'm in
agent mode, so I stick to that. over
here you can uh you can select exactly
which model you're using. So like in in
earlier months I think in my previous
video that I did about cursor I was
primarily using
GPT40 cuz I think at the time that's
what it was defaulting to since then
Claude from Anthropic came out with
Claude 3.7 and 3.7 Sonnet. There's 3.5
summit sonnet. There's this max thing.
Honestly, I haven't really spent enough
time like reading up on what the
difference is between these, but I have
found that Claude seems to be more
accurate and more useful in my coding
work, especially in Ruby on Rails
projects. So, that I think is what it's
using most of the time, but now it just
auto selects. And I keep that option
turned on. Most of the time I don't even
really know which LLM model is actually
being used. I actually find that this
auto option is really good. All I know
is that more times than not, it's more
and more accurate in its responses. To
me, it it's incredible to me how much
better cursor and these AI models in
general have gotten. Like just in the
last like 3 months, 3 4 months ago, it
was probably like 50% of the time it was
giving me good information. 50% of the
time I would just reject it and say like
that's not what I what I want. I'm
finding like 80% plus more. Most of the
time it's giving me code suggestions,
changes that I actually do want to want
to apply and I'm finding that I need to
fix it far less than when I did earlier.
So, I really like this auto select
option. I keep that turned on and uh and
I keep it in agent mode. So, that's what
I'm doing. So, uh, if you haven't seen
it already, you can, uh, use this
feature up here to pull in specific
files to bring into the context that the
AI is going to read when it when it
takes your prompt and it gives you a
suggestion. So, I think by default, it's
going to uh pull in whatever file you
are currently looking at. Um, but if you
know that you're going to ask it a
question or or prompt it and you need it
to reference say a handful of other
specific files in your codebase, uh, you
can do that. Now, of course, cursor is
designed to be sort of plugged into your
entire codebase, but there are so many
files in your codebase that it's it's
not going to always use the smartest
approach to find the right ones to
reference. And and I'm going to get to
this in a minute. If if my prompts are
very targeted, I also want to be
targeted in which files it's looking at.
So, you can click this this button or I
like to use uh option command P. And I
want to pull in um let's pull in
pre-checks. And you won't really know
what all these things mean. They're sort
of specific to my project that I'm
currently working on here. Let's do uh
in road map. And then I can give it a a
prompt. So I'm right now I'm in the in
the process of like really refactoring
how uh components are installed into a
host rails application. Again, that's
more in the weeds on my own project
here, but it's something that's going to
involve this refactoring is going to
involve multiple files. So, you know
what? Another thing I'm I'm actually
doing this in my day-to-day is I'm
finding that I'm I'm typing a lot of
prompts into cursor and my fingers are
actually getting tired from like typing
all these words. Um, so I'm actually
trying to use dictation a lot more. So,
I'm going to go ahead and do that. So, I
can do control the the control key
twice. I do that. refactor my
installation process so that if it's the
primary component then we will build the
components road map and then uh cycle
through all of the components that are
in the array of components to install
and uh and run the installation process
that way. I didn't really phrase that
exactly how I wanted it, but um I think
that's that's good enough at least just
for this example. So, I'm going to send
that and we're going to wait a minute
for it to um kind of process and look at
these relevant files that I gave it to
look at. One other thing that I noticed
lately um with the more recent updates
to cursor and bringing in these other
models like cloud 3.7, it actually takes
a little bit longer than it used to to
uh to analyze and search and generate
its suggestion. Especially when the
prompt that I asked it is sort of
complex and and I know that they're
going to be like multiple changes that
are going to be happening here. The
other thing is that I'm recording this
at 10:30 a.m. Eastern time on a
Wednesday. And I am I am definitely
finding that it's a little bit slower as
we get near the middle of the of the
business workday, at least here in the
US. Uh which tells me there are
definitely some like high traffic
periods in cursors, uh servers, and and
infrastructure that that tend to kind of
slow it down. But here we go. We we've
got uh we've got some some refactoring
here. So, my workflow here would be
would be to kind of go through and and
read most of this. I'll be honest, a lot
of times I sort of just skim it. Um, but
I do sort of read to see what exactly
were the changes. The other thing I
really like and I don't I think this is
fairly new in in my file cursor is going
to show me not only show me these
changes obviously in green and and if it
got rid of anything it'll it'll be in
red, but I like this on the right edge
there's this like green highlight. So
when I have like a really long file, it
can sometimes be hard to find um the
exact spot in the file where where these
changes are. So I can always find them
that way. The other thing that they've
really improved is this interface down
here. So I can sort of cycle through the
different changes. And I was hoping that
in this case it would have made changes
to multiple files, but it actually
didn't. You know, in that case it has
this thing where I can click review next
file. And sometimes like the changes
that it'll make will involve like four,
five, six different files and I can just
go through one by one and and click next
file or review next I think it says. Um
maybe I'll try to come up with an
example of that. You know cursor and the
interface has come a long way just in
the last couple of months to make all
this a lot clearer. So you know I can
accept which I usually do with command
well I guess it's command Y but I I
believe command return. Yeah, it sort of
accepts everything. command Y will
accept like the specific um line that
you are currently looking at. And you
know, normally I do go through and I
sort of read it line by line to see
exactly what was changed um and why and
then uh maybe I can spot things that I
still want to tweak. You know, another
tip here is in addition to pulling in
specific files that I wanted to
reference, there are a lot of times when
I want it to just focus on a very
specific section of code. And so I do
this a lot where I I will highlight, you
know, just a couple of lines of code or
a specific method that I wanted to edit
and I'll click add to chat or I could
just do command L. And you'll see here
that it added not only the file but also
these lines 98 to 105. Um and then I I
might say like is there a better way
to
refactor this method call? This one is
sort of it is what it is. Um, but it's
going to like analyze that specific
call. So, all I said was like refactor
this method call and this means the
thing that I actually highlighted. So,
it's going to focus on these lines of
code right here. Now, here's something
that I think cursor probably will
improve in in the future. Uh, but it's
still a little bit confusing if you're
new to it. So, here's what happened
here. I asked it a question about a
specific section of code. And the first
part here, this is not actually the
suggested change. All it's doing here is
it's referencing. It's saying like the
current code is this, right? It's sort
of like like just pointing to it. That
that's what this block is. But cursor
also has this button, I guess, which is
always built into these little code
blocks like apply to this page um or
apply to this file. But there's nothing
to actually apply here. This is just a
reference point. So I feel like in the
future cursor cursor's interface should
be smarter about that to know when the
AI is just referencing a section of code
versus when it's actually something more
like this where it is actually
suggesting an edit. Um and the other
thing I think this is because I'm in
agent mode. You'll see it already has
the check mark or these buttons where I
can accept the change. Meaning in this
case I don't have the button to click to
apply to my codebase because in I think
in agent mode it's automatically going
to apply it or it's automatically going
to make the change. My only next step is
to review it and then accept. Um in this
case I was actually happy with uh with
the previous one. So I I will reject
that. I think the other way to reject
everything I think is command delete. Oh
it's uh shift commanddee. Yeah. So that
will that will sort of like reject
everything if I want to sort of like
undo or or go back. Okay. So now I've
just got two more tips here which are
more highlevel uh strategic more about
how I go about prompting. So the first
one is that I really try to be as
targeted as possible. So this is getting
back to the idea of quote unquote vibe
coding. I think the term vibe coding
tends to refer to, and maybe I'm wrong
about this, but it could be people who
don't really know how to program and and
really haven't learned and really aren't
full stack developers, but they're using
AI to uh sort of lead the way and build
out a product, and they don't
necessarily know what all the code that
it's spitting out is doing, which is
fine. It's pretty cool. I I I happen to
think it's a good thing to empower
people to be able to build stuff when
they weren't capable and have the
knowledge on how to build stuff before.
That's that's great, I think. But for
full stack developers like myself and
I'm guessing like you if you're watching
this video or maybe you're learning Ruby
on Rails or you're learning how to code
which I still think is a valid and a
really good thing to do in this career.
We can use and we can leverage AI at a
much higher a much deeper level right
and so that's why I'm finding that I'm
actually prompting the AI a lot more
these days than I am writing actual
code. So when I'm prompting AI, most of
the time I'm being highly targeted,
right? I know exactly the system that
I'm building, that I'm assembling here
in my product. Um, so I'm using the AI
as my assistant to execute the changes
that I want to make to my system. I know
exactly how my system works. I know
exactly what every method and every file
and every line of code is doing because
I'm being very intentional about how I'm
crafting my product, but I don't
necessarily have to be the one to write
out every line of code. And that's where
being highly targeted about it. So
instead of saying like build a whole
feature, build, you know, um build a
whole billing system for me go. Yeah,
you can do that and and it'll start to
spit out a bunch of code that you can
pop into your project and but I find
that you're going to be far less
accurate that way and it's going to have
a lot of mistakes. It's going to have a
lot of things that just don't make
sense. It's going to build some things
that maybe you didn't ask for because
you were way too broad. I much prefer to
say like all right in this method we're
just going to set up the uh
initialization for uh the installation
of this component and uh I want to
design it this way with this method has
to execute uh these three tasks and um
and yeah write write this section of
code for me. So, I I really like to be a
much more targeted. And even though it's
going to require more prompts and more
highly targeted code edits, I'm finding
those are going to be much more accurate
and much more useful and productive in
what I actually want to build, which
ultimately in the long run is going to
save me a lot of time rather than asking
it to just here's one prompt to build an
entire feature and now I need to dig
through and find all the mistakes and
find all the things that I want to undo
and change. That's that's a messy way to
do it. I much rather uh prefer this
highly targeted approach. That to me is
the difference between vibe coding and
actually building or coding with AI.
Another tip, and I just started doing
this recently, I'm finding it very
helpful is especially when I'm uh
debugging or troubleshooting a really
tricky issue. Obviously, when you're in
a project, if you if you come across
like an error, if if the whole thing
fails, you could obviously just, you
know, highlight that error and pop it
into the chat and uh the AI will
immediately read the error and try to
find the solution. But other times,
there are things that happen that don't
necessarily error out um but they are
unexpected results or the thing didn't
work um according to your design. And so
in those cases, what I used to do was I
would spend a lot of time prompting and
describing like I was expecting this
outcome, but instead I got that outcome
and I think it's something like this and
I think the problem might be here. Tell
me how to fix that problem. Right? I I
might phrase the the prompt in that way.
But I'm finding that a better approach
is to so like for example here is a
Rails project where I'm testing out my
components gem and the components gem
generates a a lot of this uh output in
the console. So, here was like a a big
installation process and some things
were successful and some things were
failed and there were things that
happened out of order and there were
probably a bunch of uh different
problems that I am aware have happened.
But what I'm going to do is I'm going to
highlight all of this and I'm going to
bring it back into my project where I'm
working on this gem and I'm going to
say, you know what, I'm going to dictate
it. That'll that'll be easier. I'm going
to paste the output from the terminal
when I ran the authentication generator
and I want you to find and list the
issues that you're seeing and then I
will decide which one or ones we want to
fix and then I'm going to paste all of
that output from the console right right
below I'm going to send and so what this
is going to do is you know it's going to
analyze the output and then it's going
to literally give me like a numbered
list of the uh the issues that it's
seeing. And again, like I know what the
most important problems are, but what
I'm doing here is I'm making sure that
the AI can identify those same problems.
And sure enough, the one that I know
that I'm that I'm actually fixing today
is this first one. Duplicate content uh
component installations. Long story.
It's a It's a really tricky thing that I
need to fix, but I'm glad that that was
the first issue that it also identified.
So, it's it's sort of a way to confirm
that my AI assistant and myself are on
the same page. We're both seeing the
same thing. And now I can, you know,
proceed to um and I mean, it it
identified a couple of other issues too
that I'll probably get around to fixing,
but this first one is the most
important. And so now that it identified
that, now I can say like yes uh suggest
uh the best approach to fixing the
duplicate uh component installation
problem. Okay. So now that it has
identified the right problem to solve.
Um so it has that context, now I can go
ahead and prompt it to suggest uh a fix
for that. So I'm going to go ahead and
do that. Yes, the first issue duplicate
component installations. Please give me
your best suggestion on an approach to
fix that. Okay, so that was sort of a
long one and uh it did go ahead and give
me some suggestions. Again, this is one
of those things where it's sort of like
pointing to uh to some code, but then
here it gave me some uh some code edits
and it made those code edits actually in
a couple of different files. I can see
down here, this is a new part of the
interface where it says that it edited
two files. I don't really use that much.
But as I said earlier, I can find the
these suggestions that it has already
made by looking at the right edge here.
This is what I tend to look at most is I
can find those things right here. Here's
a big chunk of code that it added and
then it added a couple bits down here
and I can accept this file and then I
love this new feature where I can just
click review next file. So that's going
to hop over to my other file where it
removed a bit of code here and it added
a bit of code here. And then I can just
accept all command return and I'm good
to go. So that's the update on what my
current workflow is looking like as I
use cursor. As I said it it keeps
changing every couple of months uh
because you know cursor keeps rolling
out these updates which is fantastic.
But you know, as you saw in this video,
I'm working heavily in Ruby on Rails and
I happen to be building a gem for Rails
in in instrumental components. And you
know, I did another entire video
specifically about building with AI for
Ruby on Rails. It's called Ruby on Rails
on AI. And it's why I happen to think
that the Ruby coding language,
programming language, is perfectly
optimal for this new era of coding with
AI. I think it's an interesting take. I
firmly believe it. I invite you to check
it out and let me know what you think.
So, thanks for watching.